[Music]
welcome comrades thank you for joining
us today I have a very special guest
with us
I have CIA whistleblower John Kerry aku
John key please introduce yourself to
our viewers and subscribers and where
can we or where can they find your work
oh sure thanks
my name is John Kiriakou I'm a former
CIA counterterrorism officer I blew the
whistle on the CIA's torture program in
2007 I'm a former senior investigator
with the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee and counterterrorism
consultant for ABC News
but it's the whistleblowing that's sort
of put me front and center on these
human rights issues I'm on Twitter at
jQuery aku I'm on Facebook John Kiriakou
and John Kiriakou calm all right thank
you John so let's start from the
beginning
what what made you join the CIA in the
first place and what was it if you
collaborate on the various roles that
you that you held what was that like
you're so I was in grad school at George
Washington University and I was taking a
class called the psychology of
leadership best class I ever had in grad
school taught by an eminent psychiatrist
by the name of Gerald post and he gave
us an assignment one day where he wanted
us to shadow our bosses and write a
psychological evaluation on them and so
I was working for a labor union at the
time called the United Food and
Commercial Workers Union it's the
largest union within the afl-cio and I
was a little bit afraid of my boss he
was one of these old-school union
organizers he had had his back broken by
scabs on the picket line one time and
just a mean old school tough guy and so
halfway through the week we got into an
argument and I called him a racist which
he was and he got so angry his face got
red and he bunched up balled up his
fists and he's
to set a stance and I remember that
recoiling a little bit because I thought
well here comes now I've gone and done
it and he looked at me and he says my
penis is bigger than yours I said what I
said I quit you're nuts and I quit and I
walked out I quit this in my paper
thought that he was a sociopath with
psychopathic and possibly violent
tendencies Wow
I always did not expect that part so I
sent it in and the next week I got my
paper back and the professor gave me an
A and in the in the column in the
right-hand column he wrote I agree with
your assessment I believe he's a
sociopath with psychopathic tendencies
please see me after class and so after
class I said dr. post you wanted to see
me yes he says come down to my office so
I went down to his office he closed the
door and he turns he says look I'm not
really a professor here I'm the CIA
officer undercover as a professor here
and I'm looking for people who might fit
into the CIA's culture he said I like
your writing style would you like to be
in the CIA Wow sure why not and so I
started the process it took a while but
you know there are so many levels of
testing and investigations and
polygraphs and all kinds of stuff but
eventually I made it through the process
and a year later I was working at the
CIA Wow and then what what were the
roles that you held there well I started
off in the Directorate of intelligence
as an analyst I was in something that
used to be called the the Office of
leadership analysis it no longer exists
but I was assigned to Iraq this was in
December of 1989 January 1990 nothing
ever happened in Iraq ever it was the
same cabinet since the 1968 revolution
right we didn't even have diplomatic
relations with them I mean we did but it
was just barely
we had just you know a four person
embassy and so I was told
take your rock learn how to how to do
CIA style analysis we're going to teach
you we're
send you to the writing course and
you'll learn the CIA writing style and
then when you get good enough to do it
will transfer you onto something
interesting like Romanian that's what
they told me something interesting like
Romania well just when I got to the
point where I really believed I knew
what I was doing I was and I had a
degree in Middle Eastern Studies my
focus was on Islamic theology my
Master's was in policy analysis so I had
this skills in the background once I
really figured out what I was doing
Iraq invaded Kuwait we went to war with
Iraq in the first Gulf War and drove
them out and I was the go-to guy I was
Saddam Hussein's biographer in the
intelligence community and so because I
knew so much about the Iraqi leadership
I was sent out before the war to to live
with the Koidu royal family in exile in
Saudi Arabia I was the liaison to the
Kuwaiti resistance as they were going
across the border into Kuwait to blow up
Iraqi tanks and installations and stuff
like that I did that for three and a
half years then I went to a year of
full-time Arabic training and then
overseas as the economic officer at the
American Embassy in Bahrain I returned
as a senior Iraq officer and did that
for another two and a half years and
then I got bored and so I made a very
unusual switch from from analysis to
operations as it turned out I was the
only person in the entire CIA who spoke
both Greek and Arabic and there was a
counterterrorism slot in Athens looking
at Arab terrorism and so I went through
the the operational training found that
I actually had a knack for it and I went
to Athens working counterterrorism I
came back to headquarters in 2000 2001
the September 11th attacks take place
and then I go out as the chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
post 9/11 did some really cool things
there caught Abu Zubaydah who we thought
was the number three in al-qaeda so when
I went back
quarters I became the executive
assistant to the CIA's deputy director
for operations and then I went to the
United Nations after that and I left I
retired in places what they say I left
from the United Nations okay and then
you also touched on this in the in the
intro a little bit but if you can
elaborate on what means you blow the
list on the CAE a answer and the CAA and
just describe the whistleblowing process
yeah that's a good question because in
2007 there was no process when I got
back from Pakistan I was asked by a
senior officer in the counterterrorism
center if I wanted to be his words
trained in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques I had never
heard that term before and I asked him
what it meant and very excitedly he said
we're gonna start getting rough with
these guys I said what's that mean and
so he sort of delineated these ten
techniques that were gonna be used and I
said buddy that sounds like a torture
program to me and he said no it's not
torture we got approval from the White
House and the Justice Department I said
let me think about it for an hour so I
went upstairs to the executive floor and
and I I asked for five minutes with a
with a very senior CIA officer for whom
I had worked in the Middle East a decade
earlier and I said they just asked me if
I wanted to do this thing that they're
calling enhanced interrogation what do
you think of that and he said first of
all let's call it let's call it what it
is he said it's a torture program they
can use whatever euphemism they want but
this is a torture program and secondly
torture is a slippery slope and you know
how these guys are somebody's going to
go overboard and they're gonna kill a
prisoner and when that happens there's
going to be a congressional
investigation and then there's going to
be a Justice Department investigation
and somebody's gonna go to prison do you
want to go to prison I said no I don't
want to go to prison it turned out I was
the only person who went to prison but I
said no no I don't want to go to prison
I went back downstairs and I said this
is a torture program and I want nothing
to do with it
and in my mind this was so illegal
it was so unethical
that I just assumed somebody would come
out and say something and nobody ever
did so two years later I resigned from
the agency to go into the public to the
private sector rather and and I still
waited for somebody to say something
finally after another three and a half
years this is five and a half years
after the fact I decided I would say
something and so bright up the rest of
my life I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners I said the
torture was official US government
policy it was not the result of a rogue
CIA officer which is what President Bush
had said and I said that the that the
torture program had been personally
approved by the President himself
and so as you can imagine within 24
hours the CIA filed what's called a
crimes report against me
with the Justice Department the FBI
investigated me for a year from December
of oh seven to December of oh eight and
then in December going they sent my
attorneys what's called a declination
letter declining to prosecute me they
said that I had not committed a crime
four weeks later Barack Obama is
inaugurated and he names John Brennan an
old enemy of mine deputy national
security advisor I had no idea that John
Brennan then asked the Justice
Department to secretly reopen the case
against me and so for the next three
years my phones were tapped my emails
were being intercepted teams of FBI
agents were following me everywhere and
in January of 2012 right this is four
years after I blew the whistle I was
arrested and charged with five felonies
including three counts of espionage
right so that's interesting so what why
do you think the Obama administration
was so harsh on whistleblowers versus
the Bush administration I think it was a
combination of John Brennan and Eric
Holder Obama had a nick Sounion
obsession with national security leaks
and I know that that came from John
Brennan because I had friends in the
White House at the time telling me that
John Brennan is really getting the
president revved up about leaks that
that old-timers said that they hadn't
seen
anything like this since Richard Nixon
was president and so I say this all the
time this is something I think that's
very important the Espionage Act was
signed into law in 1917 it was written
to combat German saboteurs during the
first world war between 1917 and 2009 it
was used three times to prosecute
Americans who had spoken with the media
just in the eight years of the Obama
administration he charged eight people
with espionage for speaking to the media
it was used as a weapon unlike anything
that any previous president had ever
done and this was at the urging of of
John Brennan and Eric Holder right and
then also around that same time where
you were blew the whistle
there was another whistleblower sergeant
Joseph Darby who her viewers are not
familiar with this the Abu Garbi great I
I'm sorry Abu Ghraib whistleblower you
know it didn't seem like he got the same
treatment as you why do you think that
is because he was military and there's
an entirely different system for the
military I was civilian and the National
Security Division of the Justice
Department takes no prisoners
don't forget to this is how these guys
get promoted you know these prosecutors
and assistant US Attorney's these
Justice Department functionaries they
don't get promoted if if they don't
initiate prosecutions and so they do two
things to ensure those those convictions
they do something called venue shopping
which means they charge you in the
federal district court where they
believe they're most likely to get a
conviction and that's usually the
Eastern District of Virginia no national
security defendant has ever won a case
in the Eastern District of Virginia
that's where I was charged Jeffrey
sterling Julian Assange ed Snowden we're
all charged in the EDB a the other thing
that they do is called charge stacking
where even if they believe you've
violated a law they'll charge you with
10 15 20 fell
and they'll wait until you go bankrupt
and then they come to you and say okay
we'll drop all these charges if you
plead guilty to one felony well
ProPublica
published a study in November 2012 in
which they found that the federal
government wins ninety eight point two
percent of its cases so do you really
want to roll the dice knowing that you
have a 1.2 percent chance I'm sorry one
point eight percent chance of of winning
you know like for me because they charge
tacked me as well I was facing 45 years
in prison they're offering me 30 months
amount in 23 I had five kids at home so
you know what do you do everybody takes
the deal everybody in fact I'll tell you
a funny story I just reminded one of my
attorneys of this yesterday I was
talking to him the Justice Department
made its best and final offer 30 months
do 23 I stayed up all night long with my
wife we were gone over Harvard Law
Journal papers and I was the only person
ever charged with this crime so no there
was no case law nobody else had ever
been charged and I decided this is crazy
as soon as I get in front of a jury
they're gonna realize how stupid this is
and so I called my lawyers early in the
morning and I said I'm gonna turn down
the deal I'm going to trial they drove
straight over to my house this was very
early on a Saturday morning like 7 a.m.
and one of them pulled me aside it was
the the attorney I like them all they
were great the Washington Post called
them legal Titans but I left this one
the most and I and I respected him the
most and he pulled me aside he said you
know what your problem is your problem
is you think this is about justice and
it's not about justice it's about
mitigating damage take the deal and
that's what convinced me to take the
deal because he was right there are a
lot of innocent people in prison I came
to learn that firsthand I met a lot of
them it's not about justice it's about
getting the best possible deal yeah
unfortunately that's how the system is
and hopefully that can change
you know the as we were pointing out
earlier the Obama administration was
known for prosecuting whistleblowers
such as yourself do you think there's
any indication that the Trump
administration will break Obama's record
in prosecuting whistleblowers good
question you know when when Donald Trump
was first inaugurated I gave an
interview to MIT press News and they
asked me a similar question did I think
that Donald Trump would carry on Obama's
policy of prosecuting whistleblowers and
I said I can't imagine anybody being
worse than Barack Obama the fake phony
progressive Barack Obama in his war on
whistleblowers I said my guess is that
Donald Trump has more of a libertarian
streak and he'll probably back off that
was foolishly naive in fact we've seen
so far in the whistleblower cases
brought by the Trump Justice Department
not only are they getting convictions
like Obama was but the sentences are
longer and now they've essentially
kidnapped Julian Assange you know Julian
is looking at a very real possibility of
dying in prison right and that's that's
a very tragic oh my god it's just so
minute so many aspects of and also
Chelsea Manning as well exactly right so
many aspects of both of their stories
are are so horrible they're so chilling
like you you can't even imagine that
this takes place in the United States
but it does it does every day and you
have to blame the mainstream media as
well where the heck is the Washington
Post and The New York Times you know
they they know they'll do front page
editorials on Jamal keshavjee and what a
terrible terrible thing it was that he
was executed but isn't it equally
terrible that the Justice Department is
prosecuting a publisher if they
successfully published punish Julian
Assange what's to keep them from going
after the Washington Post right and but
also these mainstream outlets don't they
have a close tie with these agencies
and that's the real scandal look at
Kendall a nyan as my favorite example
Kendall a nyan is the so-called national
security correspondent at NBC and MSNBC
formerly of the Los Angeles Times
so Jason Leopold of BuzzFeed did a
Freedom of Information Act request in
which he asked for copies of all
correspondence between the CIA's Office
of Public Affairs and all mainstream
reporters and what he ended up finding
was that Kendall a nyan of NBC and MSNBC
was writing articles and sending them to
the CIA for approval before he even sent
them to his own editors right you know
it's not journalism when you take the
CIA's press release change a couple of
the words and the positions of the
paragraphs and put your name at the top
of it and run it in the newspaper that's
not journalism and what happens is the
CIA knows that it's that it's successful
it's going to be successful when it does
this they say look treat us right
publish this or don't publish that or
we're never talking to you again and
you're finished in Washington and they
all cower in fear before the CIA's
Office of Public Affairs right and so so
knowing what you know and have
experience within the CIA do you think
that this agency you know causes more
harm than good
should it be abolished or do you think
he serves some purpose no I don't think
it serves any purpose John Kennedy
famously said in October of 1963 just
weeks before he was assassinated that he
wanted to break the CIA into a thousand
pieces and scatter it to the wind that
never happened but there were others who
thought similarly like Senator Daniel
Patrick Moynihan of New York who wrote a
book in 1976 about abolishing the CIA
and he was a conservative Democrat and
still believed that the CIA should be
abolished I've come to the conclusion
that the
CIA is just simply unnecessary the State
Department's Bureau of intelligence and
research does better analysis than the
CIA does the Department of Defense has a
bureau called defense human services
defense human intelligence services they
go through exactly literally exactly the
same training in human source
recruitment that the CIA does they could
do the human source recruitment and then
in terms of technology and technological
development we have NSA and we have
DARPA so why compete we don't need ia
right I agree and also I'm just curious
to see what you say about this what do
you think is the most pressing issue
that no one is talking about right now
wow that's a tough one overall yes you
know in 1993 Bill Clinton instituted a
new policy at the CIA
it became derisive Lee known as the cull
C ull the new policy was we were going
to go through the files of literally
every recruited asset in the world and
if those assets had any human rights
problems in their past they were gonna
be fired
right and they actually did it it took
about two years but they fired fully
one-third of all the recruited assets in
the world and I remember thinking wow
Bill Clinton has some balls he was
serious about this like human rights is
really a thing now and the CIA whether
they like it or not they're gonna have
to respect human rights and then
September 11th happened and then the
mantra was kill them all so you had new
executive orders from the White House
you had executive order 12333 this is
the ban on assassinations which was
revoked then you had secret prisons than
you had secrets renditions and then you
had a secret torture program and if
anybody got in the way you just killed
them that's I think the most important
thing that nobody's talking about right
now
Wow there were a number of times when I
was still at the CIA where we gave an
order for example for a kidnapping
and several of us I was I was a
mid-level manager at the time several of
us went to the Director of Operations
and we said listen this is the wrong guy
we've made a mistake here no there's no
mistake this is the guy we're like now
we think this is not the guy well the
guy was sent to Syria where he was
tortured mercilessly for 18 months they
raped him
they gave him electric shock they pulled
out his fingernails and then this came
back to us and said listen we think this
is the wrong guy Wow and they let him go
we've never apologized we never sent
made any settlement because you can't
sue the American government well this
happened multiple times to multiple
people where we were wrong it was the
wrong guy and so you end up with well
there was a there was an Egyptian
national who lived in in Germany and we
snatched him off of a bus and sent him
back to Egypt where they tortured him
like an animal and then they came back
and they said it's not the guy well when
he went into the torture chambers in
Egypt he was you know he looked like you
or me and he ran a grocery store when he
came out he had a beard down to his
waist and he was carrying a copy of the
Quran and talking about how he wanted to
kill Americans well that's our fault we
did that we radicalized him and his
friends and his family members and then
multiply that by all the villages that
we've bombed and all the weddings that
we've bombed and all the funerals that
we've bombed right dirge for terrorism
what's no wonder everybody hates us
right and you know it it's a terrorist
organization and you know that the CIA
you know before breakfast tries to
actively overthrow and to stabilize any
state that defies us hegemony so I I
kind of want to touch touch back on
we were just talking about about how can
the CIA be a Bosch or overthrown like
well the Empire will just have to
crumble or or do you think it's feasible
to actually overthrow the surveillance
state I don't I I think it's too
embedded it's too well financed it has
too much support from know-nothing
Americans at the same time I'm I'm a
realist and I understand there's not
going to be a popular action to
overthrow this surveillance state yeah I
think that it has to be done
incrementally we've had some successes
in Congress for example at scaling back
slightly but still scaling back
for example the Patriot Act or some of
NSA's surveillance authorities also I
recommend to to college students I speak
at colleges and universities all the
time and people invariably wait in long
lines to ask me how they can get into
the CIA and even after all that I've
told them after all that I've said in
these speeches they still want to go to
the CIA and I tell them you know if you
go to the CIA you're gonna find yourself
around year 10 of your career as
suddenly being in a position of
authority and if you have any brains and
maybe some foreign language capabilities
you're going to continue to get promoted
and you're gonna be able to change the
CIA from the inside you're gonna be able
to respect human rights and civil rights
and civil liberties and you're gonna be
able to stand up to the policymakers
this is one of the reasons why I hate
when the CIA has generals or admirals
heading it because generals and admirals
became generals and admirals by saying
yes sir right and you don't want
somebody to say yes sir you want
somebody to say mr. president let me
tell you why that's a terrible idea
let me tell you why we shouldn't be
doing that and mostly ia directors don't
have the guts to say something like that
right there they're programmed to be
robots
yeah that's yes men yes exactly
before I add to that yeah look at John
Brennan as as an exam exactly John
Brennan's the perfect example John
brennon Washington's a small town right
and and there aren't too many different
circles in which people like us formerly
of the intelligence community travel
John Brennan will tell everybody in
Washington who is willing to listen how
much he wants to be Secretary of Defense
and so it's better for him to have been
a robot it's better for him to have been
a yes-man
because he wants to be the Secretary of
Defense in his next iteration that's a
great example and then we also we have a
question from our from my another host
Paul yeah I wanted to bring it to sorry
we're kind of reforming this a little
bit Julian Assange sits in kind of a
really weird I know we're kind of
bringing it back from CIA a little bit
but in in the context of whistleblowers
Julian Assange is in this weird place of
being sort of persecuted by the United
States via extradition while not even
being an American citizen like I wonder
if you have any thoughts of like how
that compounds his situation and if you
have any insight as to like maybe advice
even for what he should be doing or his
legal team
maybe I meet regularly with his
attorneys I don't want to give away any
secrets but but this is literally
unprecedented this is something that
nobody's ever had to fight before we've
never charged a foreign national right
with espionage like this especially one
who's clearly a journalist and publisher
and so literally everything in this case
every part of this case is
precedent-setting which i think is very
very dangerous you know there's another
thing to that poor Julian is going for
they're going through his his prison
sentence in the UK expired nine days ago
he was sentenced to 50 weeks in prison
for bail-jumping it's a am I allowed to
swear on this yes it's total [__]
charge right totally [__] they just
made it up as a way to hold him
because when the reason I say it's
[__] is because there was no
criminal charge to back it up right he
jumped bail on this sexual assault thing
and the sexual assault thing was
withdrawn so technically he didn't jump
bail but anyway not only did they hold
him in prison they held him in
maximum-security Belmarsh prison in
solitary confinement with the worst
serial killers the worst most depraved
criminals in all of the United Kingdom
beyond that his sentence expired nine
days ago he did the sentence but the
United States asked the UK to keep him
in Belmarsh until we're darn good and
ready to send the FBI's jet to London to
pick him up and render him back to the
United States look everything about this
is illegal everything about it is
inappropriate so I will say the hope
that I have for him is he has some of
the best legal minds in both Washington
and London behind him with that said
he's being tried in the Eastern District
of Virginia where I said earlier nobody
has ever won a national security case
there and worse than that I complained
bitterly in writing and in TV interviews
that his judge was my judge and Jeffrey
Sterling's judge and ed Snowden's judge
Leonie brinkema a hanging judge former
prosecutor in the Justice Department's
National Security Division in fact that
has changed now where Julian will not be
tried by Leonid brinkema he's going to
be tried by the chief judge of the
Eastern District of Virginia and guess
what he did before he was the chief
judge he was the chief judge of the FISA
Court so there's no such thing as a fair
trial for Julian Assange and there is
especially no such thing as a fair trial
in the Eastern District of Virginia
yeah and that's that's a total shame
what they're doing to Julian we can only
hope that he gets out and he gets to
recover and get the treatment that he
desperately needs because his work and
such and and the likes of your work as
well are desperately needed Thank You
Anna in this yes Tara
time it's a terrible time but we can't
forget about Chelsea Manning Elsie
Manning yeah her work is desperately
needed she is definitely a hero and she
is being mistreated as well she's back
in there's a solitary confinement he's
in general population in a population in
the federal holding facility at
Alexandria and in addition to that and
mind you this is a contempt charge she's
not been convicted of any crime right
she just they wanted her to go against
Julian yes and to contradict herself
right what is they subpoenaed her they
said we want you to testify before the
grand jury she said no they said that
she said everything I said or everything
that you would ask me I said in my own
trial all you need to do is submit the
transcript for the record it answers all
the questions but what they wanted her
to do was to say something differently
than what she said in her own trial
because then they can charge her with
perjury with statement so she did
something incredibly brave braver than
what I would have done what she could
have done is go before the grand jury
and just say in response to every
question I don't recall you know well
where do you live what's your address I
don't recall what did Julian Assange
tell you on this date
I don't recall and there would be
literally nothing they could do to her
but she didn't do that she said that
this was a violation of her fourth and
sixth amendment rights to the
constitution and by God if that meant
going to jail she was going to go to
jail and not only has she lost her
freedom but she's being fined $1,000 a
day for every day that she doesn't
testify she's lost her home she's lost
everything that she had worked for you
know she was she was making money giving
speeches and traveling and the LGBTQ
community has taken really great care of
her she's lost all of it it's all gone
and that that's a shame and like again
we we are major supporters of Julian
Assange Snowden and Chelsea Manning and
we hope that you know we can
you know get them home you know so we
can come home one day Chelsea you can
get out and quickly julian assange can
get out and be free as well because
those those people are heroes for sure
you are too and we would like to thank
you again for joining us
pleasures all mine and before we wrap up
please
remind our viewers where they can find
your work
you bet so let's see I've got a podcast
every day called loud and clear that's
on all the platforms I Heart Radio
iTunes Spreaker Spotify I'm on Facebook
and Twitter
Facebook's John Kiriakou Twitter's at
jQuery aku and I'm at John Kiriakou calm
well thank you John and then the the
people that are watching this right now
please stay with us we have another
interview coming right up
thank you again for joining us and thank
you John for taking the time to speak
with us thank you
[Music]
yeah